<chapter name="Cross sections and weights"> 
 
<h2>Cross Sections and Weights</h2> 
 
Although Pythia's baseline setup is for generating sets of fully 
unweighted events (each representing an equal fraction of the total 
generated cross section), some options and interfaces 
allow for, and even mandate, generation of weighted events. 
Methods related to retrieving both the integrated cross sections 
computed by Pythia as well as various kinds of event weights are 
collected on this page. 
 
<h3>Cross Sections and Weight Sums</h3> 
 
Here are the currently available methods related to the event sample 
as a whole, for the default value <code>i = 0</code>, and otherwise for 
the specific process code provided as argument. This is the number 
obtained with <code>Info::code()</code>, while the further subdivision 
given by <code>Info::codeSub()</code> is not bookkept. While continuously 
updated during the run, it is recommended only to study these properties 
at the end of the event generation, when the full statistics is available. 
The individual process results are not available if 
<aloc href="SecondHardProcess">a second hard process</aloc> has been 
chosen, but can be gleaned from the <code>pythia.stat()</code> output. 
 
<method name="vector&lt;int&gt; Info::codesHard()"> 
returns a vector with all the process codes set up for the current run, 
i.e. the valid nonzero arguments for the five methods below. 
</method> 
 
<method name="string Info::nameProc(int i = 0)"> 
returns the process name for process code <code>i</code>. 
</method> 
 
<method name="long Info::nTried(int i = 0)"> 
</method> 
<methodmore name="long Info::nSelected(int i = 0)"> 
</methodmore> 
<methodmore name="long Info::nAccepted(int i = 0)"> 
the total number of tried phase-space points, selected hard processes 
and finally accepted events, summed over all allowed processes 
(<code>i = 0</code>) or for the given process. 
The first number is only intended for a study of the phase-space selection 
efficiency. The last two numbers usually only disagree if the user introduces 
some veto during the event-generation process; then the former is the number 
of acceptable events found by PYTHIA and the latter the number that also 
were approved by the user. If you set <aloc href="SecondHardProcess">a 
second hard process</aloc> there may also be a mismatch. 
</methodmore> 
 
<method name="double Info::sigmaGen(int i = 0)"> 
</method> 
<methodmore name="double Info::sigmaErr(int i = 0)"> 
the estimated cross section and its estimated error, 
summed over all allowed processes (<code>i = 0</code>) or for the given 
process, in units of mb. The numbers refer to the accepted event sample 
above, i.e. after any user veto. 
</methodmore> 
 
<method name="double Info::weightSum()"> 
Sum of weights accumulated during the run. For unweighted events this 
agrees with the number of generated events. In order to obtain 
histograms normalized "per event", at the end of a run, histogram 
contents should be divided by this weight. (And additionally 
divided by the bin width.) Normalization to cross section also 
required multiplication by <code>sigmaGen()</code> below. 
</method> 
 
<method name="int Info::lhaStrategy()"> 
normally 0, but if Les Houches events are input then it gives the 
event weighting strategy, see 
<aloc href="LHA">Les Houches Accord</aloc>. 
</method> 
 
<h3>Event Weight</h3> 
 
<method name="double Info::weight()"> 
weight assigned to the current event. Is normally 1 and thus 
uninteresting. However, there are several cases where one may have 
nontrivial event weights. These weights must the be used e.g. when 
filling histograms. 
<br/>(i) In the <code><aloc href="PhaseSpaceCuts"> 
PhaseSpace:increaseMaximum = off</aloc></code> default strategy, 
an event with a differential cross-section above the assumed one 
(in a given phase-space point) is assigned a weight correspondingly 
above unity. This should happen only very rarely, if at all, and so 
could normally be disregarded. 
<br/>(ii) The <aloc href="UserHooks">User Hooks</aloc> class offers 
the possibility to bias the selection of phase space points, which 
means that events come with a compensating weight, stored here. 
<br/>(iii) For Les Houches events some strategies allow negative weights, 
which then after unweighting lead to events with weight -1. There are 
also Les Houches strategies where no unweighting is done, so events 
come with a weight. Specifically, for strategies <ei>+4</ei> and 
<ei>-4</ei>, the event weight is in units of pb. (Internally in mb, 
but converted at output.) 
<br/>(iv) If enhanced parton shower emissions are activated, the corrective 
weight to each event containing enhanced emissions is included here. 
</method> 
 
<h3>CKKW-L and NLO Merging Weights</h3> 
 
<method name="double Info::mergingWeight()"> 
combined leading-order merging weight assigned to the current event, if 
tree-level multi-jet merging (i.e. 
<aloc href="CKKWLMerging"> CKKW-L</aloc> or 
<aloc href="UMEPSMerging"> UMEPS</aloc> merging) is attempted. 
If tree-level multi-jet merging is performed, all histograms should be 
filled with this weight, as discussed in 
<aloc href="CKKWLMerging"> CKKW-L Merging</aloc> and 
<aloc href="UMEPSMerging"> UMEPS Merging</aloc>. 
</method> 
 
<method name="double Info::mergingWeightNLO()"> 
combined NLO merging weight assigned to the current event, if 
NLO multi-jet merging (i.e. 
<aloc href="NLOMerging"> NL<sup>3</sup></aloc> or 
<aloc href="NLOMerging"> UNLOPS</aloc> merging) is attempted. 
If NLO multi-jet merging is performed, all histograms should be filled 
with this weight, as discussed in 
<aloc href="NLOMerging"> NLO Merging</aloc>. 
</method> 
 
<p/> 
Note that there are two schemes to handle the combination of merging 
weight and event weight. These can be selected by using the setting 
 
<flag name="Merging:includeWeightInXsection" default="on"> 
If on, then the reweighting of events in the CKKW-L scheme is included 
in the event weight <code>Info::weight()</code>, the merging weight 
<code>Info:mergingWeight()</code> is unity, and the cross section 
printed by <code>Info::sigmaGen()</code> includes the effect of CKKW-L 
merging. 
</flag> 
 
<h3>User Hooks Weight</h3> 
 
<method name="virtual double UserHooks::biasedSelectionWeight()"> 
Returns the weight you should assign to the event, to use e.g. when 
you histogram results. It is the exact inverse of the weight you 
used to modify the phase-space sampling, a weight that must be stored 
in the <code>selBias</code> member variable, such that this routine 
can return <code>1/selBias</code>. The weight is also returned by the 
<code>Info::weight()</code> method, which may be more convenient to use. 
</method> 
 
<h3>Shower Uncertainty-Variation Weights</h3> 
 
As discussed in the sections on Parton Showers, the user can 
request Pythia to compute (sets of) alternative event weights 
representing (groups of) variations of shower parameters. 
See <ref>Mre16</ref> and the page on 
<aloc href="Variations">Automated Variations</aloc> for further 
documentation. 
 
<p/> 
The following methods give access to the groups of uncertainty weights: 
 
<method name=" int    Info::nVariationGroups() "> 
  returns the number of groups 
</method> 
<method name=" string Info::getGroupName(int iG) "> 
  returns the name of the iG-th group 
</method> 
<method name=" double Info::getGroupWeight(int iG) "> 
  returns the weight of the iG-th group 
</method> 
 
<p/> 
Correspondingly, the individual parameter-variation weights can also 
be accessed: 
 
<method name="int Info::nWeights()"> 
  returns number of individual parameter-variation weights 
</method> 
<method> name="string Info::weightLabel(int i)"> 
returns label of i-th individual parameter-variation weight 
</method> 
<method name="double Info::weight(int i)"> 
  returns value of i-th indivudal parameter-variation weight 
</method> 
 
<p/> 
Note, <code> weight(0) </code> returns the same value as 
<code>weight()</code>, 
which is the baseline weight for each event (normally unity for an 
ordinary unweighted event sample). The individual parameter-variation 
weights are thus enumerated starting from <code>1</code> for 
the first up to <code>nWeights()</code> for 
the last individual parameter variation. 
 
<h3>The Weight Container</h3> 
 
In the long run, we plan to consolidate all possible weights into 
one structure with a simple getter for the user. This strategy 
is currently used when producing <code>HepMC2</code> and 
<code>HepMC3</code> output. In these two cases, all weights 
that appear in the event generation will automatically be 
transferred to the output files. This means that the HepMC file will 
automatically contain weights from various sources, e.g. weights from 
<aloc href="LHEF">LHE files</aloc>, 
<aloc href="Variations">automated shower variations</aloc>, etc. Note that 
for LHEF files, only the <ei>detailed format</ei> is currently 
supported in the weight container, and that the names of weights 
appearing in HepMC will use the convention discussed in 
<ref>But14</ref>, page 162.  The sample main programs 
<code>main44.cc</code> and <code>main45.cc</code> 
illustrate this behaviour. 
 
<p/> 
In this context, the following program methods are relevant: 
 
<method name="int Info::numberOfWeights()"> 
The total length of the set of all weights, similar to 
<code>Info::nWeights</code> above (which returns the length of the set 
of shower variation weights). 
</method> 
 
<method name="string Info::weightNameByIndex(int i)"> 
Returns the name of the i'th weight.  For example, if "i" indexes a 
shower variation, this would e.g. return <code>fsr:muRfac=0.5</code> 
and so on. If "i" pertains to a weight read from an input LHEF file 
(see <aloc href="LHEF">Les Houches Event Files</aloc> for further 
details), then the name will be returned in the convention discussed 
in <ref>But14</ref>, page 162. These latter names are constructed from 
the content of the "&lt;weight&gt;" tags in the LHE file header. 
</method> 
 
<method name="double Info::weightValueByIndex(int i)"> 
Returns the value of the i'th weight. The normalization of all weights 
is synchronized. For unweighted event generation (as would be the case 
when running stand-alone, of for LHEFs employing weight strategy 3), 
the value is relative to the cross section. For weighted events 
(e.g. when using LHEFs employing weight strategy +-4), the value will 
include the cross section prefactor. <code>main44.cc</code> gives an 
example for both these cases. 
</method> 
 
<method name="vector &lt;string&gt; Info::weightNameVector() const"> 
Returns a vector of all weight names. The ordering of entries in synchronized 
with the order of <code> Info::weightValueVector()</code>. 
</method> 
 
<method name="vector &lt;double&gt; Info::weightValueVector() const"> 
Returns a vector of all weight values. The ordering of entries in synchronized 
with the order of <code> Info::weightNameVector()</code>. 
</method> 
 
<p/> 
Custom weights such as shower variations weights, shower variation group 
weights, and weights directly included from LHEF input receive an 
<code>AUX_</code> prefix in the weight name as reported by the methods 
<code>Info::weightNameByIndex</code> and <code>Info::weightNameVector</code> 
to mark them as auxiliary output. This allows the user to further process or 
combine the weights in a meaningful way. Since the number of these weights 
depends on the LHEF input, different numbers of weights might occur in the 
output when processing multiple LHEF input files. To avoid this, the following 
flag allows to suppress the output of <code>AUX_</code> weights. 
 
<flag name="Weights:suppressAUX" default="off"> 
If on, the output of weights with <code>AUX</code> prefix will be 
suppressed in the five above mentioned methods. The nominal weight and 
combined weight variations from LHEF, parton shower and merging 
remain. 
</flag> 
 
</chapter> 
 
<!-- Copyright (C) 2022 Torbjorn Sjostrand --> 
