<chapter name="Hadronic Rescattering"> 
 
<h2>Hadronic Rescattering</h2> 
 
This page describes a model for hadronic rescattering. (Not to 
be confused with partonic rescattering, an optional part of the 
<aloc href="MultipartonInteractions">Multiparton Interactions</aloc> 
framework.) Specifically, it is assumed that the hadrons produced 
can scatter against each other on the way out, before the fragmenting 
system has had time to expand enough that the hadrons get free. This 
is happening in parallel with rapid decays, i.e. mainly strong such. 
 
<p/> 
A prerequisite is that the space-time production vertices of hadrons 
from string fragmentation are known. This was implemented in 
<ref>Fer18</ref>, and is described separately on the 
<aloc href="HadronVertexInformation">Hadron Vertex Information</aloc> 
page. A smaller further smearing is obtained from the 
<aloc href="PartonVertexInformation">Parton Vertex Information</aloc> 
transverse displacement of separate MPI vertices. 
 
The main on/off switch for rescattering is 
<code>HadronLevel:Rescatter</code>, which by the default is off, since 
rescattering slows down the generation of events considerably, and since 
there are no detailed tunes with rescattering as of yet. The model 
requires space-time information on hadron production vertices to be set, as 
obtained with <code>Fragmentation:setVertices = on</code> and optionally also 
<code>PartonVertex:setVertex = on</code>. 
 
In some studies not all events are of interest, for example if studying 
jet production and no jets with sufficently high <ei>pT</ei> are produced. 
In those cases, it is possible to save a significant amount of time by 
vetoing the event before rescattering has take place, by overriding the 
<code>canVetoAfterHadronization</code> and 
<code>doVetoAfterHadronization</code> methods of the 
<aloc href="UserHooks">UserHooks</aloc> class. 
 
<p/> 
Technically, the processes here are the same as used in the 
<aloc href="QCDLowEnergyProcesses">Low-energy QCD Processes</aloc> 
framework, i.e. it is the same partial cross sections and the same 
hadronization setup that is used in both cases. The two play different 
functions, however, either representing the primary collision as there 
or secondary rescattering collisions as here. 
 
<p/> 
The implementation is rather sophisticated for rescattering at low 
energies, where the vast majority of interactions occur. It is less 
appropriate at higher energies, where the lack of MPIs leads to too 
few hadrons being produced. The rescattering rate becomes vanishingly 
small before that is a problem, however. What this simplification buys 
is the capability to switch between different colliding hadron 
combinations without any need for a reinitialization. 
 
<p/> 
Currently there are only a few options available: 
 
<modepick name="Rescattering:impactModel" default="1" min="0" max="1"> 
Impact-parameter shape of the opacity, i.e. rescattering 
probability, with a width determined such that the current 
rescattering cross section is reproduced, given the maximal 
opacity below. 
<option value="0">Solid disk with constant opacity out to a sharp edge. 
</option> 
<option value="1">Gaussian fall-off of the opacity.</option> 
</modepick> 
 
<parm name="Rescattering:opacity" default="0.9" min="0." max="1."> 
Gives the probability of scattering at impact parameter 0. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="Rescattering:bMax" default="5." min="0." max="100."> 
Maximum allowed impact parameter for a rescattering to occur, 
expressed in units of fm. This cuts off the tail of a Gaussian 
impact-parameter profile, and more generally puts a (generous) 
limit on how large a cross section can become. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="Rescattering:tau0RapidDecay" default="100." min="10."> 
For hadrons with a nominal invariant lifetime below this value, 
expressed in fm, their decays are considered in the same time-ordered 
sequence as rescatterings, while the rest of the decays are considered 
separately after the rescatterings. Note that the actual lifetime is 
drawn from an exponential distribution, with the nominal lifetime 
giving the average value. 
</parm> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:scatterManyTimes" default="on"> 
When on, particles that have rescattered can scatter again. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:quickCheck" default="on"> 
When on, a quick check is made that a pair of hadrons that is moving 
away from each other cannot rescatter. This is done in the CM frame 
of the event, not in that of the pair itself as done later. It therefore 
rejects a small fraction (order 10%) of rescatterings that would have 
been acceptable when viewed in the pair rest frame, but with a 
significant gain in event generation time. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:nearestNeighbours" default="on"> 
Allow or not hadrons that have been produced as nearest neighbours 
on a string to rescatter against each other. There is no matter of 
principle to forbid it, but such effects implicitly are already 
included in current tunes without rescattering, so to include it 
will require a larger retuning effort than not to. If off also 
forbid hadrons that already scattered (primarily elastically) 
to immediately scatter against each other again. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:delayRegeneration" default="on"> 
If on then forbid a scattered hadron from scattering again within 
a given regeneration time, while if off a hadron can scatter 
immediately afterwards. This applies to hadrons that emerge directly 
from the scattering, i.e. mainly in elastic and excitation. It is 
also relevant for the undiffracted hadron in single diffraction. 
Hadrons produced via string fragmentation automatically get a time 
delay by that. The size of the delay is given by the next parameter. 
</flag> 
 
<parm name="Rescattering:tauRegeneration" default="1." min="0." max="2."> 
When a hadron should be assigned a regeneration invariant time this is 
done according to an exponential with average value given by this 
parameter, expressed in units of fm. 
</parm> 
 
<modeopen name="Rescattering:boostDir" default="0" min="0" max="3"> 
Direction of boost below, 0 off, 1 - 3  give x, y and z respectively. 
</modeopen> 
 
<parm name="Rescattering:boost" default="0."> 
Boosts the event before rescattering, by this many units of rapidity. 
For testing purposes. 
</parm> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:useVelocityFrame" default="off"> 
Use center of velocity instead of center of momentum to determine rescattering 
origin. 
</flag> 
 
<flag name="Rescattering:inelastic" default="on"> 
If turned off, all rescatterings will be treated as elastic. Used primarily 
for model tests. 
</flag> 
 
<h3>Nucleon excitations</h3> 
 
<p/> 
In rescattering, nucleon-nucleon interactions can produce resonance particles. 
This is implemented as <ei>N N &rarr; N X</ei> or <ei>N N &rarr; Delta X</ei>, 
where <ei>N</ei> is a nucleon (<ei>p</ei> or <ei>n</ei>), <ei>Delta</ei> 
refers to a <ei>Delta(1232)</ei> particle, and <ei>X</ei> is a nucleon 
excitation such as <ei>p(1520)+</ei> or <ei>Delta(1600)+</ei>. For the sake of 
efficiency, the relevant cross sections are parameterized ahead of time. This 
is handled by the <code>NucleonExcitations</code> class. 
 
<p/> 
For all excitation processes, the cross section is independent of the isospin 
of the involved particles. This means that the calculations can be 
simplified by using &quot;id masks&quot; of the various particles. We define 
the mask of a particle as its id code with the quark content removed. 
For example, the <ei>p(1520)+</ei> particle (<code>id = 102214</code>) 
has mask 100004, which is the same for <ei>n(1520)0</ei>. 
 
<p/> 
The following methods of the <code>NucleonExcitations</code> class are 
available. 
 
<method name="bool NucleonExcitations::check()"> 
run a check to validate the loaded cross section data. Returns whether 
successful. 
</method> 
 
<method name="vector&lt;int&gt; NucleonExcitations::getExcitationMasks()"> 
search the particle database and returns a list of id masks for all 
implemented nucleon excitations. A particle is defined as a potential 
nucleon excitation if its quark content is <ei>uud</ei> (except for 
<ei>p+</ei>). 
</method> 
 
<method name="vector&lt;pair&lt;int, int&gt;&gt; 
NucleonExcitations::getChannels()"> 
returns a list of all parameterized excitation channels. Each returned 
<code>pair</code> contains the masks of the two outgoing 
particles. For each excitation <ei>X</ei> (as defined by 
<code>getExcitationMasks</code>), there are two possible excitation 
channels, <ei>N N &rarr; N X</ei> and <ei>N N &rarr; Delta 
X</ei>. Note that the masks for <ei>N</ei> and <ei>Delta</ei> are 
<code>0002</code> and <code>0004</code>, respectively. 
</method> 
 
<method name="double NucleonExcitations::sigmaExTotal(double eCM)"> 
returns the total excitation cross section for two nucleons colliding at the 
specified CM energy, using parameterized values. 
</method> 
 
<method name="double NucleonExcitations::sigmaExPartial(double eCM, 
int maskC, int maskD)"> 
returns the cross section for the process <ei>N N &rarr; C D</ei> at the 
specified CM energy, using parameterized values. 
</method> 
 
<method name="bool NucleonExcitations::pickExcitation(int idA, int idB, 
double eCM, int& idCOut, double& mCOut, int& idDOut, double& mDOut)"> 
pick an excitation channel for the incoming particles with the specified 
CM energy, using parameterized cross sections. If successful, the outgoing 
particle ids are written to <code>idAOut</code> and <code>idBOut</code>, 
and their corresponding masses are written to <code>mAOut</code> and 
<code>mBOut</code>. Returns whether successful. 
</method> 
 
<method name="double NucleonExcitations::sigmaCalc(double eCM)"> 
</method> 
<methodmore name="double sigmaCalc(double eCM, int maskC, int maskD)"> 
calculate the total excitation cross section or the partial cross section 
for the process <ei>N N &rarr; C D</ei>, without using the parameterized 
cross sections. 
</methodmore> 
 
<method name="bool NucleonExcitations::parameterizeAll(int precision, 
double threshold = 8.)"> 
clear all parameterized cross sections and recalculatesthem for all possible 
excitation channels, using excitations found with 
<code>getExcitationMasks</code>. 
</method> 
 
<method name="bool NucleonExcitations::save(ostream& stream)"> 
</method> 
<methodmore name="bool NucleonExcitations::save(string 
file = &quot;HadronWidths.dat&quot;)"> 
write all parameterized cross sections in an xml format to the 
specified stream or file. 
</methodmore> 
 
</chapter> 
 
<!-- Copyright (C) 2022 Torbjorn Sjostrand --> 
