<chapter name="Parton Vertex Information"> 
 
<h2>Parton Vertex Information</h2> 
 
While the setting of secondary production vertices of unstable 
hadrons and leptons is a standard part of the particle decay 
rotines, no corresponding standardized handling is in place for 
the evolution in the partonic or hadronization phases 
of the event generation. The intention is to provide such methods 
in due course. 
 
<p/> 
There are some cases where such information is needed already now, 
specifically for the 
<aloc href="RopeHadronization">Rope Hadronization</aloc> and the 
<aloc href="HadronicRescattering">Hadronic Rescattering</aloc> 
frameworks. Therefore the beginning of a framework is available, 
that can be used to set impact-parameter-plane vertices for 
partonic production by MPI, FSR, ISR and beam remnants. This is 
done in the <code>PartonVertex</code> class. 
 
<p/> 
This is a base class, with a default implementation, but the user 
can replace it with a derived class that does a more sophisticated 
handling. Improvements and extensions are likely to come to the 
base class. So, while people are welcome to write their own derived 
classes, it is likely that these may need to be modified in later 
PYTHIA versions. 
 
<h3>Hadronization Parameters</h3> 
 
Currently the base class implements a few alternative approaches to 
picking a partonic vertex, for use inside the rope hadronization and 
hadronic rescattering frameworks. There are also some free parameters 
in the models. 
 
<flag name="PartonVertex:setVertex" default="off"> 
Master switch to allow the setting of partonic vertices. 
</flag> 
 
<modepick name="PartonVertex:modeVertex" default="2" min="1" max="4"> 
Choice between alternative procedures to select vertex. 
<option value="1">Proton profile is a (Lorentz-contracted) 
uniform-parton-density ball. This gives an almond-shaped 
overlap region between two colliding hadrons, favouring MPI being 
displaced perpendicularly to the collision plane. 
</option> 
<option value="2">Proton profile is a (Lorentz-contracted) 
three-dimensional Gaussian, or equivalently a two-dimensional one, 
since a Gaussian easily factorizes so that the <ei>z</ei> can be 
integrated out. This gives a Gaussian overlap region between the 
two colliding hadrons, since the product of two displaced Gaussians 
is another Gaussian. 
</option> 
<option value="3">Proton profile is a Gaussian, as above, but 
elongated by a scale factor <ei>rEps</ei> in the <ei>x</ei> direction 
and compressed by the same factor in the <ei>y</ei> direction. 
Here <ei>rEps = sqrt( (1 + epsilon) / (1 - epsilon) )</ei>, where 
<ei>epsilon</ei> is described further below. If <ei>epsilon &lt; 0</ei> 
then the role of elongation and compression is exchanged. 
</option> 
<option value="4">Proton profile is Gaussian, as above, but with a 
further modulation factor <ei>1 + epsilon * cos(2 * phi)</ei>, where 
the asymmetry parameter <ei>epsilon</ei> is described further below. 
The azimuthal angle <ei>phi</ei> is defined with respect the the 
hadron-hadron collision plane. Among rotationally symmetric parton 
distributions only the Gaussian one (or a sum of Gaussians) do not 
give rise to azimuthal asymmetries, so this option offers some 
further flexibility. 
</option> 
<note>Warning:</note> In the first option collisions cannot happen 
if the impact parameter is larger than twice the proton/hadron radius. 
The MPI machinery has a separate framework for selecting impact 
parameters, however, by default closer to option 2, and thus able 
to produce larger separations. To this end, the impact parameter 
is limited to be at most 0.95 of the maximal in option 1, 
and a warning is issued for values initially above that. 
</modepick> 
 
<parm name="PartonVertex:phiAsym" default="0." min="-0.9" max="0.9"> 
The azimuthal asymmetry parameter <ei>epsilon</ei> defined above for 
<code>PartonVertex:modeVertex =</code> 3 and 4. A positive (negative) value 
favours MPI production in (out of) the collision frame, as could be 
expected for a matter distribution with a flatter-(sharper-)than-Gaussian 
edge. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PartonVertex:ProtonRadius" default="0.85" min="0." max="10."> 
The proton radius and shape depends on the collision energy and on the 
context in which it is used. The default value is based on the static 
charge-radius definition. If the DIPSY model <ref>Fle11</ref> is used, 
then for a description at LHC collision energies, say 14 TeV, the required 
profile corresponds roughly to a Gaussian with a width of around 0.7 fm. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PartonVertex:EmissionWidth" default="0.1" min="0." max="10."> 
Vertices of ISR+FSR partons are smeared relative to their mother by a 
Gaussian distribution with a width of <code>EmissionWidth</code>/<ei>pT</ei>, 
where <ei>pT</ei> is the transverse momentum of the produced parton (in GeV). 
This parameter thus determined the overall strength of the transverse space 
smearing. 
</parm> 
 
<parm name="PartonVertex:pTmin" default="0.2" min="0.05" max="1."> 
The parton transverse smearing is assumed proportional to <ei>1 / pT</ei>, 
but <ei>pT</ei> is limited to be above this parameter so as to avoid 
unreasonable values. 
</parm> 
 
<flag name="PartonVertex:randomPlane" default="on"> 
If off then the impact parameter vector lies in the <ei>xz</ei> plane, 
which is convenient for theoretical studies of azimuthal distributions. 
If on then the event will be rotated a random angle around the z axis 
so as to be more realistic. The angle can still be reconstructed from 
the vertices of the two incoming hadrons. 
</flag> 
 
<h3>External models</h3> 
 
A derived class for setting parton vertex information can be provided 
to PYTHIA with the 
<br/><code> 
bool Pythia::setPartonVertexPtr( PartonVertex* partonVertexPtrIn) 
</code><br/> 
method. The methods in the derived <code>PartonVertex</code> class 
can then be used to add vertex information to produced particles, 
at creation time, in MPI, FSR and ISR and beam remnants. The assigned 
vertex information will afterwards be accessible as properties of the 
individual particles. Particles produced in other types of processes 
than the ones mentioned above will not have vertex information 
assigned (e.g. hard process), neither will particles produced in the 
weak shower. 
 
<method name="virtual void init()"> 
can be used to initialize various parameters of the model or precalculate 
common numbers. Note that a separate non-virtual method will already 
have provided pointers to the <code>Info</code>, <code>Settings</code> 
and <code>Rndm</code> classes, so that these are available in all derived 
classes. 
</method> 
 
<method name="virtual void vertexMPI( int iBeg, int nAdd, double bNow, 
Event& event)"> 
Method to assign a production vertex to a particle produced in the MPI 
framework. Should set the vertices <code>vProd</code> of the particles 
concerned. 
<argument name="iBeg"> is the index of the first parton of a MPI. 
</argument> 
<argument name="nAdd"> is the number of partons involved in the MPI, 
currently always four: two in and two out. 
</argument> 
<argument name="bNow"> is the impact parameter of the event. It is not 
expressed in physical units (like fm), but rescaled such that the average 
is unity for MPI events. See the section on 
<aloc href="MultipartonInteractions">Multiparton Interactions</aloc> for 
a description of choices for the <ei>b</ei> dependence. 
</argument> 
<argument name="event"> reference to the whole event, to read information 
from and set the relevant <code>vProd</code> values into. 
</argument> 
</method> 
 
<method name="virtual Vec4 vertexFSR( int iNow, Event& event)"> 
Method to assign production vertex to a particle produced in the FSR 
(<code>TimeShower</code>). Should set the vertex <code>vProd</code> 
of the particle concerned. 
<argument name="iNow"> is the index of the parton concerned. In a 
branching the daughters automatically inherit the vertex of the mother, 
if it has one, and similarly for the recoiler. This method is called 
specifically for what is considered the emitted parton of the process, 
i.e. the gluon in a <ei>q &rarr; q g</ei> branching, and allows the 
vertex of this parton to be modified. 
</argument> 
<argument name="event"> reference to the whole event, to read information 
from and set the relevant <code>vProd</code> values into. 
</argument> 
</method> 
 
<method name="virtual Vec4 vertexISR( int iNow, Event& event)"> 
Method to assign production vertex to a particle produced in the ISR 
(<code>SpaceShower</code>). Should set the vertices <code>vProd</code> 
of the particle concerned. 
<argument name="iNow"> is the index of the parton concerned. This method 
is called three times for each ISR branching, for the daughter, the 
new recoiler and the sister. 
</argument> 
<argument name="event"> reference to the whole event, to read information 
from and set the relevant <code>vProd</code> values into. 
</argument> 
</method> 
 
<method name="virtual void vertexBeam( int iBeam, vector&lt;int&gt;& iRemn, 
vector&lt;int&gt;& iInit, Event& event)"> 
Method to assign production vertices for the beam itself and the beam 
remnants. 
<argument name="iBeam"> is 0 and 1, respectively, for the two beams. 
The two beam particles are then located in event record positions 1 
and 2, and normally you would set them to be displaced <code>+-bNow</code> 
along the <ei>x</ei> axis. 
</argument> 
<argument name="vector&lt;int&gt;& iRemn"> are the indices of the beam 
remnants that could be displaced by you. 
</argument> 
<argument name="vector&lt;int&gt;& iInit"> are the indices of the initiator 
partons for all the MPIs of the event. They already had their vertices 
assigned and should not be changed. But that information could be used 
e.g. to ensure that the energy-weighted average of all initiators and all 
remnants together give the proper beam impact parameter. 
</argument> 
<argument name="event"> reference to the whole event, to read information 
from and set the relevant <code>vProd</code> values into. 
</argument> 
</method> 
 
<method name="virtual void vertexHadrons( int nBefFrag, Event& event)"> 
Method to shift hadron production vertices by an amount related to 
that of the partons they come from. This may be the most complicated 
step of them all, since there is not a unique one-to-one association 
between a hadron and a parton. 
<argument name="nBefFrag"> is the size of the event record before the 
latest fragmentation step, and <code>event.size()</code> the one 
after. All the hadrons in that range come from the fragmentation of 
the partons given by their common mother indices, and are open to 
receive modified production vertices. 
</argument> 
<argument name="event"> reference to the whole event, to read information 
from and set the relevant <code>vProd</code> values into. 
</argument> 
</method> 
 
</chapter> 
 
<!-- Copyright (C) 2021 Torbjorn Sjostrand --> 
